<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wuhan Virus | Nam&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>/vi/tags/wuhan-virus/</link>
      <atom:link href="/vi/tags/wuhan-virus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Wuhan Virus</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>vi</language><copyright>© 2022 Nam Le</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 01:58:39 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Wuhan Virus</title>
      <link>/vi/tags/wuhan-virus/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>100 Câu Hỏi Của Tiến Sĩ Peter Piot, Giám Đốc Đại Học LSHTM</title>
      <link>/vi/post/100questionsofpeterpiot-covid19/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 01:58:39 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/vi/post/100questionsofpeterpiot-covid19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;tế-bào-virus-chủng-mới-corona&#34;&gt;Tế Bào Virus chủng mới Corona&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/news/1280px-Coronavirus_virion_structure.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chú thích:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spike Glycoprotein S:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;E protein&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Membrane Protein M&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RNA genome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Envelope&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bài-gốc&#34;&gt;Bài gốc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bài gốc của cuộc phỏng vấn được đăng trên trang web của Đại Học London School of Hygiene &amp;amp; Tropical Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lshtm.ac.uk/newsevents/expert-opinion/100-questions-peter-piot-lshtm-director?linkId=85296289&amp;amp;fbclid=IwAR1Z8ze1Nae08m2FhEyQtCV0nvZt1DzJwjfMAv9OCaT5hxbGfphIIFrZosw&#34;&gt;100 Questions of Peter Piot, LSHTM Director&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;số-liệu-thống-kê-covid-19-ở-việt-nam&#34;&gt;Số Liệu thống kê Covid-19 ở Việt Nam&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;đôi-điều-về-tiến-sĩ-peter-piot&#34;&gt;Đôi điều về tiến sĩ Peter Piot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nội-dung-cuộc-phỏng-vấn&#34;&gt;Nội dung cuộc phỏng vấn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hãy bắt đầu với một câu hỏi cơ bản. Một tế bào virus là gì?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virus (siêu vi trùng) là một phần tử siêu siêu nhỏ của đoạn mã &lt;a href=&#34;https://vi.wikipedia.org/wiki/RNA&#34;&gt;RNA&lt;/a&gt; hoặc &lt;a href=&#34;https://vi.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA&#34;&gt;DNA&lt;/a&gt; được bảo vệ bởi một lớp vỏ bọc protein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virus có phổ biến không?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virus ở khắp nơi. Sự ngạc nhiên ở chỗ nếu bạn thu gom toàn bộ số virus trên trái đất và đem đi cân thì khối lượng của chúng còn lớn hơn toàn bộ các cá thể sống trên trái đất, bao gồm tất cả các loài thực vật, động vật và vi khuẩn. 10% gen của người là từ DNA của virus. Có thể nói trái đất của chúng ta là một &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;hành tinh virus&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tại sao việc khống chế sự lây lan của virus lại khó khăn đến vậy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bởi vì các phần tử virus là siêu siêu nhỏ, các hạt nước nhỏ li ti bắn ra sau một cái ho của ai đó nhiễm virus có thể chứa hàng tỷ phần tử virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bạn không tin thì xem cái video này? (Không có trong nội dung phỏng vấn - người dịch tự thêm vào)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vBvFkQizTT4?enablejsapi=1&amp;color=white&amp;autoplay=1&amp;start=12&amp;end=24&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sau khi xem xong cái video này, hẳn các bạn thấy tác dụng của việc đeo khẩu trang và sẽ đồng ý rằng tại sao số người nhiễm và chết ở Châu Âu, Mẽo cao vậy, là do bởi tụi dâu ngô này toàn ôm nhau và hôn hít nơi công cộng. Xưa mình ở Thụy Sĩ, đi xe bus cũng thấy chúng nó sờ mó nhau, đúng là khủng bố tinh thần anh em châu Á như mình.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thật sự là virus nhỏ thế nào?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siêu siêu nhỏ, nhỏ đến độ mà không thể nhìn thấy virus bằng một kính hiển vi thông thường. 100 triệu phần tử virus có thể xếp trên đầu một cái đinh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Các phần tử virus có thể làm gì?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Các phần tử virus luôn cố gắng xâm nhập vào các tế bào sống để nhân bản, làm nhiễm các tế bào khác, và từ đó làm nhiễm các sinh vật chủ khác.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tại sao virus lại phải cố gắng xâm nhập vào các tế bào sống?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phần tử virus tồn tại như các loài kí sinh trùng. Chúng cố gắng xâm nhập vào tế bào sống để nhân bản. Chúng khủng bố các tế bào sống để các tế bào này tạo ra nhiều phần tử virus. Khi một tế bào bị virus tấn công, virus có môi trường để tự tạo ra hàng trăm ngàn bản sao của chính nó. Có thế nói virus ăn tế bào cho đến khi tế bào đó chết.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bị nhiễm coronavirus (SARS-CoV2) là sao?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bị nhiễm coronavirus tức là khi virus SARSCoV2 đã bắt đầu nhân bản trong cơ thể.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sự khác biệt giữa SARSCoV2 và Covid-19 là gì?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SARSCoV2 là virus còn Covid-19 là loại bệnh do virus đó gây ra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Một phần tử virus có dễ dàng xâm nhập vào một cơ thể sống không?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Điều này phụ thuộc trước tiên vào việc tế bào có hay không loại receptor cho từng loại virus, điều này có thể so sanh như việc một cái chìa khóa thì cần có 1 ổ khóa vậy. Hầu hết virus bị ngăn chặn bởi hệ thống miễn dịch của chúng ta hoặc chúng ta không có loại receptor thích hợp cho virus đó và virus vì thế không thể xâm nhập vào tế bào. Có thể nói, 99% số virus là không có hại cho con người.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Có bao nhiêu loại virus tồn tại, và bao nhiêu trong số đó là có hại đối với con người?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trong khoảng hàng triệu loại virus, chỉ có vài trăm là có hại cho con người. Các loài/chủng virus mới luôn xuất hiện. Hầu hết trong số đò là không có hại.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;11&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trên phương diện thống kê thì cần bao nhiêu phần tử virus để cho thể lây nhiễm cho người?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thật sự là chúng ta vẫn chưa biết chính xác về điều này với virus SARS-CoV2. Nhưng có thể nói là chỉ cần một lượng rất nhỏ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;12&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phần tử virus này trong như thế nào?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV2 trông như một sợ mỳ spaghetti rất nhỏ, được cuộn tròn giống như một quả bóng và được bao bọc bởi một lớp vỏ protein. Lớp vở này có các gai hướng ra ngoài trông giống như vòng tán từ mặt trời. Chủng virus này có một đặc điểm chung như vậy, nên chúng giống như một vòng tán (corona)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;13&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Có bao nhiều loài Corona có hại cho con người?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chúng ta đã biết có 7 loại virus Corona có thể truyền nhiễm từ người sang người. 4 loại trong số này gây ra chiệu chứng cảm nhẹ, nhưng có 3 loại thì rất nguy hiểm, bao gồm loại virus corona gây ra dịch bệnh SARS và MERS, và bây giờ là loại corona mới SARS-CoV2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;14&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tại sao lại gọi là virus corona mới?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Từ mới (Novel) có nghĩa là chúng mới với loài người, chúng ta chưa biết gì về nó trước đó. Hệ miễn dịch của chúng ta đã tiến hòa trong khoảng 2 triệu năm, nhưng khi cơ thể chúng ta chưa bao giờ nhiễm loại viris này trước đó, thì có ít cơ hội ngay lập tức để cơ thể người tự phát triển được hệ miễn dịch chống chọi với nó. Sự thiếu vắng khả năng miễn dịch cùng với khả năng lây nhiễm nhanh dễ gây tổn thương của virus này, là lý do tại sao virus SARS-CoV2 gây ra sự bất ổn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;15&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sự xuất hiện của một loài virus mới có thường xuyên không?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khá hiếm&amp;hellip;nhưng vẫn xảy ra. Một số ví dụ bao gồm các virus gây ra các loại bệnh như HIV, SARS, MERS và một vài bệnh khác. Virus mới sẽ tiếp tục xuất hiện, và sẽ trở thành một vấn đề lớn với chúng ta &amp;hellip; nếu virus có khả năng lây nhiễm dễ dàng và nguy hiểm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;16&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sự lây lan của virus dễ dàng như thế nào?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV2 lây lan rất nhanh từ người sang người từ các dịch gây ra bởi ho và chạm vào các bề mặt có dịch virus. Virus này là loại virus gây ra lây nhiễm qua hệ hô hấp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;17&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virus này còn có thể lây lan qua con đường khác không?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Một nghiên cứu gần đây chỉ ra rằng nó có thể lây nhiễm qua đường tiêu hóa (phân và nước tiểu nhiễm virus), nhưng thật sự là chưa có số liệu để khẳng định điều này.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;18&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sự khác nhau giữa virus này và virus corona gây ra bệnh SARS và MERS?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Có 4 khác biệt cơ bản là:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thứ nhất, Có rất nhiều người nhiễm virus nhưng không có triệu chứng nhiễm bệnh, chính vì thế những người này có thể gây ra lây nhiễm cho người khác một cách không chủ đích, và chúng ta cũng không biết ai bị nhiễm để mà cách ly nếu không đưa đi xét nghiệm. Điều này thật sự là gây ra bất ổn lớn vì loại virus này có khả năng lây nhiễm rất cao.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thứ 2, Thống kê chỉ ra rằng 80% số người nhiễm virus chỉ có triệu chứng nhẹ như cảm lạnh hay ho nhẹ, do đó những người nhiễm không nghĩ cách ly là cần thiết và vì thế lây nhiễm cho người khác.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thứ 3, Các triệu chứng gây ra khiến chúng là dễ làm tưởng đó chỉ là các triệu chứng của bệnh cúm mùa, do đó nhiều người chủ quan và không nghĩ đến các nguyên nhân khác.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thứ 4, và có lẽ là quan trọng nhất đó là, loại virus này rất dễ lây lan từ người sang người bởi vì trong giai đoạn đầu virus này tập trung số đông ở phần trên cổ họng chúng ta và khi chúng ta ho hay hắt xì thì có hàng tỉ phần tử virus sẽ ra ngoài thông qua các bọt nước li ti, người khác hít vào và bị nhiễm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;19&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loại virus này có gây ra viêm phổi không? và còn cổ họng thì sẽ ra sao?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loại bệnh này thường bắt đầu ở cổ họng (chính vì chúng ta lấy mẫu phẩm để làm thí nghiệm từ cổ họng) và sau đó bệnh tiến triển xuống phía dưới họng, tấn công đến phổi và trở thành loại bệnh lây nhiễm qua đường hô hấp phía dưới.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;20&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chúng ta nghe đài bào nói nhiều đến từ &amp;ldquo;không triệu chứng&amp;rdquo; rất nhiều, nó chính xác là gì?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Đơn giản nó có nghĩa là người bị nhiễm virus không có biểu bệnh lý ngay cả khi đã bị nhiễm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;21&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ý ông muốn nói đến là có nhiều người nhiễm virus và không bao giờ có biểu hiện bệnh lý?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thật không may là đúng như vậy. Có rất nhiều người bị nhiễm không có biểu hiện bệnh lý trong vài ngày đâu và sau đó chỉ có ho hay sốt nhẹ. Triệu chứng này trái ngược với bệnh SARS, loại bệnh có triệu chứng bệnh lý rất rõ ràng trong những ngày đầu và chỉ gây lây nhiễm khi bệnh nhân ốm thực sự.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;22&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nếu người bị nhiễm không có triệu chứng bệnh lý, họ có khả năng lây nhiễm chứ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Điều không may là đúng như vậy, và điều đó gây khó khăn rất lớn để chúng ta làm chậm hay ngăn chặn sự lây lan của virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thế còn công việc điều chế vacines để phòng bệnh có tiến triển thuận lợi không?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khả năng cao là thuận lợi, nhưng không có đảm bảo là chúng ta sẽ có vaccine. Thất bại trong điều chế có thể xảy ra. Đơn cử là việc điều chế vaccine cho bệnh HIV, đã hơn 35 năm trôi qua, chúng ta vẫn chưa có vaccine. Tôi khá lạc quan về việc điều chế vaccine cho SARS-CoV2, nhưng chúng ta sẽ cần phải làm kiểm định lâm sàng để đảm bảo tính hiệu quả và an toàn, điều này sẽ rất tốn công sức và cả thời gian nữa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;24&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giả định rằng chúng ta sẽ thuận lợi trong việc điều chế vacinne cho virus này và vacinne sẽ được công bố sớm, vậy mất khoảng bao lâu để chúng ta có thể bắt đầu tiêm trên diện rộng cho hàng triệu người?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chúng ta sẽ có các loại vacinne tiềm năng trong vòng một hai tháng, nhưng những vacinne đó cần phải được thử nghiệm lầm sàng để đảm bảo tính an toàn và độ tin cây cho nhiều nhóm người trước khi triển khai tiêm chủng trên diện rộng, giai đoạn này có ít nhất mất cỡ 1 năm. Như vậy, khách quan mà nói thì khoảng từ 18 đến 24 tháng là có thể triển khai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;25&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tại sao lại mất quá nhiều thời gian vậy, đặc biệt là trong tình trạng khẩn cấp như hiện nay?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thật ra, không phải là việc điều chế vacinne mất nhiều thời gian, mà là việc thử nghiệm lâm sàng. Khi một loại vaccine khả thi được bào chế, thì có hàng loạt thử nghiệm sẽ được tiến hành, trước hết là trên động vật sau đó mới đến người.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;26&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chúng ta đang thự hiện đến đâu trong việc bào chế vacinne cho SARS-Covd2?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tin tốt lành là chỉ sau vài tuần sau khi phát hiện ra virus này vào đầu tháng 1 năm 2020, việc bào chế vaccine đã được tiến hành ngay lập tức. Rất nhiều nỗ lực của các nhà nghiên cứu từ các tổ chức quốc tế và từng quốc gia đã tập trung vào công việc này.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;27&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Các nhà khoa học họ có cộng tác với nhau trong việc bào chế này không, hay là họ cạnh tranh với nhau?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Họ vừa cộng tác lại vừa cạnh tranh và điều đó không phải là điều không tốt. Có một thực tế là sự hợp tác quốc tế đã luôn là điều tốt và điều đó là đáng kích lệ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;28&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chúng ta có thể phát triển vắc xin nhanh hơn không?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Không may là không có con đường tắt. Hệ miễn dịch của chúng ta là rất phức tạp và khó tiên lượng. Sự biến đổi của virus có thể xẩy ra. Trẻ em thì khác với người lớn. Phụ nữ có thể có phản ứng khác với nam giới. Chúng ta cần phải đảm bảo rằng bất cứ loại vắc xin nào cũng phải an toàn 100% cho tất cả mọi người. Để làm được việc này, chúng ta cần tiến hành thử nghiệm thuốc và vắc xin ở rất nhiều lượng khách nhau trên một phổ rộng về độ tuổi và giới tính của các tình nguyện viên trong những điều kiện được đo lường cẩn thận.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;29&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sự nguy hiểm của chủng virus mới này ở mức độ nào?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Các nhà khoa học tin rằng tỉ lệ tử vong là từ 1% đến 2%. Tổ chức Y Tế Thế Giới (WHO) gần đây công bố tỉ lệ tử vong cao hơn 3%, nhưng các con số ước đoán này khả năng sẽ thấp hơn khi chúng ta có thống kê rõ ràng hơn, đặc biệt là với những trường hợp không được báo cáo do bị nhiễm không có triệu chứng hay chỉ ốm và cúm nhẹ sau đó tự khỏi. Có một điều chắc chắn rằng, tỉ lệ tử vong là khá cao ở nhóm đối tượng già và những người có bệnh nền, đặc biệt với phổi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;30&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Có phải tỉ lệ chết trung bình là con số ta cần quan tâm không?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Không hẳn thế, bạn có thể bị bị ngập khi mực nước trung bình là 3 inches (khoảng 10cm). Một cách tốt hơn để hiểu sự rủi do là việc nhận biết rằng nó có thể là nguy hiểm đối với từng đối tượng bị nhiễm với biểu hiện khác nhau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;31&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vậy, đâu là các con số cụ thể để chúng ta cần chú ý tới?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Như đã nói trước, 80% số người nhiễm sẽ chỉ có biểu hiện nhẹ, nhưng 20% số người nhiễm có triệu chứng nặng như số cao hoặc khó thở. Tùy vào triệu chứng biểu hiện mà có người phải nhập viện và cần có sự hỗ trợ y tế đặc biệt khi phổi của họ bị nhiễm nặng và không có khả năng làm việc bình thường nữa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;32&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nhóm người nào sẽ chịu rủi do tử vong cao?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Đầu tiên là nhóm người cao tuổi, như tôi đây nè đã 71 rồi, tuổi càng cao thì tỉ lệ tử vong gây ra bởi loại virus này càng lớn. Nhóm người có tiền sử&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, older people like me: I&#39;m 71. The older you are, the higher your risk. Also at greater risk are people with underlying diseases such as diabetes, chronic obstructive lung disease and pulmonary disease or cardiovascular disease or immune deficiencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;33&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How much danger do these  high-risk groups face?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their mortality rate can be as high as 10% or even 15%. And, your risk increases when you have more health conditions. The scientific data about all of this is regularly updated on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;34&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: So your risk increases significantly if you have other conditions, such as diabetes. Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because your immune system reacts poorly to any infectious virus, but particularly to this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;35&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: It seems that generally speaking, children and young people are only mildly affected, if at all. Is that true?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what it looks like, but as for so many other issues on COVID-19, this requires confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;36&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: If true, why would SARS-CoV2 affect older people much more, but not younger people and children?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We actually don’t know. It’s going to be a while before we figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;37&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Anything else unusual?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can infect other people even if you are totally asymptomatic and feeling fine. That’s unusual, though it can also happen with HIV infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: We often hear COVID-19 compared to the seasonal flu. What’s  the right way to frame this comparison?  For example, are the seasonal flu and coronavirus equally dangerous?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seasonal flu typically infects up to 30 million people a year in the U.S., and fewer than 1/10th of 1% of the infected group will die – but that is still a big number. Worldwide, in an average year, a total of 300,000 people die from seasonal flu. But, on an average basis, the new coronavirus is 10-20 times more deadly, and in contrast to influenza, we cannot protect ourselves through vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;39&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Does the new virus spread as easily as the flu?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new virus appears to spread as easily the flu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;40&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Continuing with the comparison of flu and COVID-19, what about causes?  Is the flu also caused by a virus?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. Flu is caused by the influenza virus. But  the influenza virus and coronavirus are very different. A flu shot doesn’t help you with the new coronavirus, but it greatly reduces your risk of flu. The common cold, for which there  is no vaccine or cure, is often caused by another type of tiny virus called a rhinovirus, and occasionally another coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;41&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How does the infection progress when the new coronavirus gets a foothold  in your body?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It usually starts with a cough. Then a low fever. Then the low fever turns into a high fever and you get shortness of breath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;42&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: At what point is good medical care the difference between life and death?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is usually when your fever is very high and your lungs are compromised so that you are short of breath or you need help to breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;43&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How is the new virus different from a disease such as the measles, mumps or chicken pox?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV2 is currently far less infectious and dangerous but there is still a lot we don’t know about it. The other diseases are well understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;44&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: If the new coronavirus is less dangerous than other viruses, why are many people so afraid of it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because new things that can kill us or cause us to be sick, make us very nervous. But accurate knowledge is the antidote to fear, so here in the U.S., I urge you to pay attention to CDC.gov.  In other countries go your national health ministry or WHO websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;45&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How often should people check the CDC or WHO websites, or the website of their national health ministry?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continuously update our knowledge as we learn more about the new virus, so these sites should be checked frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;46&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Has mankind ever wiped out a virus completely?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. Smallpox, which used to kill millions of people. And, we’re very close with polio thanks to the Gates Foundation and many governments around the world such as the U.S. Let’s not forget what a terrible plague that was in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;47&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How does the new virus get to new places around the world?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By road, air and sea. Viruses travel by airplane nowadays. Some of the passengers may carry  SARS-CoV2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;48&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: So, every international airport is a welcome mat for the new virus?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality is that SARS-CoV2 is already firmly present in most countries, including in the U.S., and far from any major international airport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;49&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Since the epidemic began in  China, do visitors from that country  represent the biggest danger of importing  coronavirus into the U.S.?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the new virus emerged in China in 2019, 20 million people have come into the U.S. from countries all over the world. The U.S. stopped most direct flights from China 4 weeks ago, but it did not prevent entry of the virus. Now cases of COVID-19 in China are often imported from other countries as the epidemic in China appears to be declining for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;50&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: In other words, major airports are all you need to guarantee that any country will have the virus everywhere in less than  3 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. I think you say in America, “The horse has left the barn.” This is not a reason to completely stop all travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;51&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Why might a country like Japan close its schools?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other countries such as Italy and France are doing the same. It’s because scientists don’t know how much of the spread is accelerated by children who are carriers. Japan is trying very hard to slow the spread. Children generally  pass along viruses quickly since they don’t wash their hands or practice much personal hygiene. They play a big role in how the flu spreads which is why many countries have been closing schools in affected areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;52&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: If I get infected, are there drugs  I can take to make the virus less severe, or make it go away entirely?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No drugs have yet been proven effective as  a treatment or what doctors call a “therapy.”  A lot of different drugs are being tested in clinical trials, so hopefully that will change  for the better soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;53&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How likely are we to come up with new therapeutic drugs, and how soon?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m quite confident that probably in a matter  of a couple of months, we are very likely to find “off-label” uses of current drugs that help treat an infected person. In other words, we&#39;ll have a new use for existing drugs that were originally used against other viral infections such as HIV. It will take time and a lot of real tests to be sure though. New therapeutic drugs are being tested in clinical trials, particularly in China, but also elsewhere. It looks promising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;54&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What about antibiotics? Everybody always turns to them in a crisis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a new virus, not a bacteria. Antibiotics work against bacteria but they do not work against viruses. They may be helpful in hospital usage with secondary infections that are bacterial, but antibiotics have no effect at all  on the new virus itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;55&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What about all kinds of new cures and therapies and treatments I’ve heard about on the Internet?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are going to be endless false claims.  Only when you read about it on multiple reliable websites, you can feel confident there  is real science. But most of what you hear will be total rubbish, so be very careful, and don’t spread unconfirmed rumors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;56&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How about masks? Are those blue surgical masks or an N95 facemask useful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Masks have very limited value except in certain specific circumstances. For example, depending on the type of N95 mask, just under 50% of inbound virus particles will be filtered out, but they may reduce spread from airborne droplets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;57&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What are the advantages of masks when used properly and who should wear masks?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best masks, carefully fitted and worn properly, slow down the spread FROM sick people coughing. Meaning, the mask is not to protect you from other people; it is to protect other people from you. It is a courtesy to others to wear a mask when you get what you think is a cold, and you start coughing. Masks have an additional benefit: they make it less likely that you will touch your mouth, so it becomes less likely that if you have the virus on your hands, you will transfer it into your body. Masks provide benefits for healthcare workers. If you work in a healthcare setting or in elder care, masks are mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;58&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Is there anything I can do to prevent from becoming infected in a global pandemic outbreak?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washing hands frequently, not touching your face, coughing and sneezing in your elbow or a paper handkerchief, not shaking hands or hugging all reduce your risk. If you are sick, stay home and consult with a doctor over the phone to see what to do next, and wear a mask when seeing other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;59&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What does “mitigation” mean?  I hear scientists using that word a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mitigation means slowing the spread of the virus, and attempting to limit its effects on public health services, public life and the economy. Until there’s a vaccine, what we can do is slow it down. That is really important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;60&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What other ways can we slow down the spread of the virus?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good hygiene and common courtesy can slow down the spread. In addition, “social distancing” measures — such as working  from home, not taking a plane, closing schools, and banning major gatherings — will help slow  the spread of SARS-CoV2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;61&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Do different viruses spread more easily than others?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. Measles is the worst. You can get measles by walking into an empty room that an infected person left 2 hours earlier! That’s why we have measles outbreaks when vaccination rates go down. It’s a very tough disease. The common cold spreads fairly easily. HIV is much harder  to spread, and yet we’ve had 32 million deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;62&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What will it take to stop this virus?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody really knows for sure, but China has shown that it is possible to stop the spread significantly. A vaccine may be necessary to fully eliminate SARS-CoV2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;63&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How long will it take for the new virus to spread through a population the size of the United States?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to spread with normal measures of good hygiene, SARS-CoV2  appears to double its infected population about every week. That means it will go from 50 people who are infected to 1 million people infected in about 14 weeks. That&#39;s the simple arithmetic of contagion.  Of course, we can do things to slow it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;64&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How effective is good hygiene in slowing down the spread of coronavirus? Do the numbers of infected people decrease noticeably if people follow the guidelines?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numbers change based on how careful people are, and even small changes are important to avoid stressing the healthcare system more than absolutely necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;65&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Can a few thousand cases be hidden among our population? How would that be possible?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year, there are millions of flu cases.  This year, some of these cases are actually COVID-19. In addition, many infected persons show no symptoms or very mild symptoms,  so they are hiding in plain sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;66&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Exactly what does it mean to test positive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It means that a sensitive test has detected that the virus is present in fluids from that person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;67&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Should everyone be tested as quickly as possible?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Testing for COVID-19 should be much more widely available because we still don’t know enough about who is infected, and how the virus spreads in the community. We need  far more testing to learn important data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;68&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Why has South Korea set up a system of “drive-through” testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Korea has drive-through testing because they are trying very hard to slow the outbreak by finding every infected person as fast as  they can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;69&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What is the main symptom that people should be on the lookout for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coughing is the #1 symptom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;70&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Is fever a good way to identify infected people?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high fever may be cause for concern and is worth getting medical attention. But screening for fever alone, at an airport or checkpoint for example, lets a lot of infected people pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;71&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What percentage of the people who tested positive in Chinese hospitals arrived without a fever?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 30% of Chinese coronavirus patients  had no fever when they arrived at the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;72&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Is the new virus likely to come back to a country again once it peaks and the number of new cases drops off?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV2 is likely to never leave us without the same effort that eliminated smallpox and has almost eliminated polio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;73&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Meaning, the only way to beat the new coronavirus in the long term is global population-wide vaccinations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We really don’t know. Population-based measures may work, but a vaccine may be necessary and is probably viable as long as the virus stays stable and does not mutate too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;74&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Might the new virus “burn out” like other viruses have seemed to do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t know, but it is unlikely. SARS-CoV2 is already too well established around the world. This is no longer just a Chinese issue; there are probably hundreds of thousands of people infected but not yet tested — not only  in China but in close to 100 other countries. SARS-CoV2, like the influenza virus that causes the seasonal flu, will likely be with us for a  long, long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;75&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Will the new virus come back in waves or cycles, and if so, when?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, we don’t know, but it is a very important question. Probably, although at this early stage, nothing is sure. The 1918 pandemic flu circled the world in 3 waves. The new virus may have  a second wave in China with the reopening of schools and factories. But until we see what actually happens, we don’t know how SARSCoV2 will behave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;76&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: If we get a “lucky” break or two in the coming months, what does being “lucky” look like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warm weather may slow down the spread, although we don’t have any evidence yet that this is the case. Singapore, which has 120 cases already, and has one of the best COVID-19 control programs in the world, is just 70 miles from the equator — so at least in that case, a warm climate has not stopped the virus from spreading. It’s possible that SARS-CoV2 could steadily mutate into a less dangerous form so that fewer people die from it, as happened before with the swine flu in 2009. But I wouldn&#39;t count on it. Quickly finding an effective drug therapy or cocktail of drugs would be excellent news. That’s about it for luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;77&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Do people who are at high risk for COVID-19 have the same chance of dying everywhere?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, your risk of death depends a lot on where you are in the world. If you need and get cared for in a well-equipped modern hospital, which we hope is accessible to lots of people, the death rate will be far lower because of intensive care respirators and fewer secondary infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;78&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: How do I know if I’m going to be in the mild group or the one that needs hospitalization?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t know for sure, but being over 70 or having a chronic condition increases your risk of severe illness, and even death. We can only speak in terms of probabilities, because we don’t yet know enough about COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;79&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Should I be worried that I’m going to get COVID-19? How worried are you, Peter?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not at high risk, I wouldn’t worry too much, but I would do everything I can to avoid becoming infected as you don’t know individual outcomes. Everyone is eventually going to be at risk for acquiring this infection in the next few years, just as no one avoids the common cold or the flu over time. So all of us should be ready to stay home at the first signs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;80&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: What do you mean everyone is going to be at risk for getting the virus?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean that all humans spend time with other humans, so we are all connected &amp;ndash; and biology is relentless. However, I would take sensible precautions and, at the same time, not worry obsessively. That isn’t helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;81&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: If everyone is going to get the new virus, why try to avoid getting it?  If I get the virus immediately, then I can be done with it and move on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to slow down the infection, which means slow down the number of new cases and total cases so our hospitals can handle the most affected patients without getting overwhelmed or turning away patients with other types of illnesses that require immediate attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;82&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: It appears that after people recover from the new virus, they may still  be contagious. Is that true?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t know, although it appears that may  be the case for a while after recovery. We are not totally sure. More research is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;83&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Once you get the virus, are you then permanently immune to getting it again, like with measles or mumps?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here again, we don’t know the answer to that important question yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;84&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Obviously, permanent immunity against COVID-19 would be important for individuals who came through one bout  of the disease. Is such immunity also important for society as a whole? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question is extremely important for the vaccine development, because vaccines rely on the ability of our body to mount a protective immune response and on a stable virus. And obviously the number of people susceptible to becoming infected would gradually decrease over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;85&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Is the new virus seasonal, like  the flu?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We haven’t gone long enough to see if there is  a seasonal mutation to SARS-CoV2, or how the trillions of new virus particles change as they pass through millions of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;86&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: So this virus can mutate by itself into new forms with new symptoms?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t know at all. If it does, new vaccines may be necessary to prevent the mutated version of SARS-CoV2 from spreading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;87&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: If the virus naturally mutates, does that mean it could become more deadly, and on the other hand, it could also become less deadly?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, either one is possible. It’s a new virus, so we have no idea what the mutations will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;88&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: If coronavirus becomes a threat that doesn’t go away, what does that mean for myself and my family?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It means we will all learn to deal with it, and make sure we are all adopting safe behaviors. We should be particularly mindful of the needs of older family members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;89&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: I heard the virus can live for  9 days on a countertop. Is that true?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s probable that SARS-CoV2 can stay viable  on some surfaces for quite a while, but we  don’t know for how long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;90&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: The greatest pandemic of modern times was the 1918 flu pandemic right at  the end of World War I. In that pandemic, influenza simply mutated – it was not a  new virus. How does SARS-CoV2 compare to that mutation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV2 is just as contagious as the 1918 influenza pandemic and appears to be nearly  as lethal, but time will tell. Remember, back in 1918 there was no medical system anything like what we have in the developed world, and there were no antibiotics to treat bacterial pneumonia, which was a major cause of death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;91&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Is there any chance that this is one giant false alarm and that we’re going  to look back this summer and say “wow,  we all panicked over nothing!”?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. COVID-19 is already in well over 100 countries and it’s highly contagious. Virtually every day there are more and more cases, in more countries. This is not a drill. It is the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;92&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: It’s hard to believe that suddenly a truly new virus that mankind has never seen can infect millions of people. When is the last time that happened?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SARS and MERS were new – but they did not reach scale. HIV was new to the world and has infected 70 million people – of whom 32 million have died from the HIV Pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;93&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: HIV affects poor countries much more than wealthier ones. Will that likely  be true for the new virus?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, absolutely. Wealthy countries such as the U.S. are going to have much lower death rates because of better hydration, supplemental breathing equipment, proper handling of infections, and the like. This is potentially a giant problem for low-resource countries that have poor health systems. Many countries in Africa will face enormous risks. When it reaches the most resource-challenged countries of the world, it&#39;s very likely to be catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;94&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: It sounds like the bottom line is that you are not terribly optimistic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I&#39;m definitely an optimist but at the same time, there is a lot to be very uncomfortable and nervous about. I understand people have fears, especially if they are in one or more of the high-risk groups. But there is also good news, because we are already seeing progress in global cooperation, especially in science and medicine. We are seeing more transparency among governments. The number of cases in China is currently rapidly declining, but that could change. And, we are seeing very rapid development of therapeutics, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;95&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: You also said there is a lot to be concerned about. What are your biggest worries for the new virus?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poorly managed, the spread of coronavirus  can quickly overload any country’s healthcare system and block people who really need all kinds of medical access. Another worry is that overreaction and fear can cripple a country’s economy, which causes another kind of suffering. So, this is a very tough trade-off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;96&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: And, what should we be psychologically prepared for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should be psychologically prepared to hear about lots of “new” cases being reported in every city in the U.S. that begins testing, as well as an increasing number of deaths, particularly among the elderly. In reality they are often not “new” cases; they are existing cases that have become visible for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;97&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TEDMED: What things are you encouraged about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern biology is moving at breakneck speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the public health community worldwide, including the World Health Organization, Government leaders at the highest levels are focusing on the threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We isolated the virus in days and sequenced it quickly. 4. I am confident we will soon have a treatment. 5. We are hopefully going to have a vaccine. 6. This is truly the age of modern communication. That can help us, as long as  we debunk fake and dangerous news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TEDMED: How ready is the U.S. for this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. has had ample time for a head start to prepare for this pandemic, and so have other high-income countries. We all benefitted from China’s unprecedented mass quarantines that slowed down the spread. The U.S. will handle the serious cases correctly from the start by being more prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;99&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Who are you most worried about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the low-resource countries that I am very worried about. Each death is a tragedy. When we say that on average, 1% to 2% of infected people will die from coronavirus, that is a lot. After all, 1% of a million is 10,000 people,  and it is the elderly I am very worried about. But 98%-99% of people won&#39;t die from this.  The seasonal flu kills tens of thousands of Americans every year and you don’t panic – even if we actually should take flu far more seriously and make sure we are all vaccinated against it every year. Just as we have learned  to live with seasonal flu, I think we will need  to learn how to go about our lives in a normal fashion, despite the presence of COVID-19, until an effective vaccine becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;100&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEDMED: Are there more pandemics in our future?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely yes. This is part of our human condition and of living on a “virus planet.”  It is a never-ending battle. We need to improve our preparedness. That means committing ourselves to seriously invest in pandemic preparedness and building a global fire brigade, long before the house catches on  fire next time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
