<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>STP | Nam&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>/tags/stp/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/stp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>STP</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Nam Le</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 08:57:31 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>STP</title>
      <link>/tags/stp/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review on Boox Note 2</title>
      <link>/post/2020-06-05-booxnote2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 08:57:31 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2020-06-05-booxnote2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/etc/booxnote2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I must say that this e-ink device looks pretty nice. 10.3 inc is perfect for me as I have tons of books in PDF and I particularly read quite a number of scientific/research papers. I have been looking for a device like this with reasonable cost for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will provide a full details pretty soon, right after the PSL, the retailer who sell this product on Lazada Philippines, exchange for me a new one as the current one has a defect that forcing the devide to restart or reboot every few minutes when turning on wifi for internet browsing and using Android app. I have been contacting with Onyx book customer team, they did send me the updated firmware and I installed it. However, the problem has not been solved. PSL understands this fact since I reported to them within few days after receiving it and they are kindly accepting me to return it and exchange for a new one. However, due to covid-16, their office in QC is partially closed, only open within a few time window in a week so till now I still have not received the replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than this critical issue, i think it is only a random error, the device itself is great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kindy bear with me sometimes after I receive a new one and try it again then I will post my review for those who desparately wanna have this note 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;05/June/2020&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequencing Batch Reactor Design and Operational Considerations</title>
      <link>/post/sbrstp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 08:57:31 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/sbrstp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/book/sbrSTP/visuals/sbr.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a copy of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.neiwpcc.org/neiwpcc_docs/sbr_manual.pdf&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; published by NEWIPCC. Copyright shall always be of the original authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I copied this in Markdown format for personal reference purpose when working with DAO2016 Compliance Assessment Projects funded by Manila Water for more than 20 Wastewater Treatment Plants (STP). Most of the STPs are SBR plants contructed many years ago and are likely not providing adequate level of service regarding the nutrient extraction capacity to satisfy the regulatory&#39;s standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/book/sbrSTP/index.html&#34;&gt;Link to the book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
